Guide to the Carlos de Francisco Zea Papers circa 1959-1990
University of Chicago Library
Francisco Zea, Carlos de
circa 1959-1990
6 linear feet (12 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Carlos de Francisco Zea (1936-1991), poet and professor, was a student at the University of Chicago and received his PhD in Germanic Language and Literature in 1970. In 1989, a book of his poems was published, entitled Libros de Poesía. Francisco Zea was an active poet throughout the years 1959-1990, and this collection contains drafts, typescripts, and manuscripts of his work. Also included are his translations of the work of Juan Ramón Jiménez.
Information on Use
Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Carlos de Francisco Zea was born into an established and intellectual family in Bogota, Colombia on November 27, 1936. Taken to Mexico by his mother he excelled scholastically at the American High School and won a scholarship to the University of Chicago. He received his undergraduate degree in 1959, winning the Goethe prize in the study of Germanic Language and Literature. In 1970 he received his PhD in Germanic Language and Literature. He taught at several institutions, including Carleton College, the University of Illinois and the City Colleges of Chicago. Carlos de Francisco Zea died on May 5, 1991.
Scope Note
This collection contains drafts, typescripts, manuscripts, and translations from the poet, Carlos de Francisco Zea.
Series I: Libros de Poesía. This series contains drafts and typescripts related to Francisco Zea’s only published book, Libros de Poesía (Barcelona: Los Libros de la Frontera, 1989). The book is divided into three suites of poems, which form the subseries of the first series in the collection. The fourth subseries contains materials related to the publication of the work. The papers were arranged by the poet and have not been altered. The poems were written from 1957 to 1987, and materials in this series span the years 1959-1990
Series II: Other Writings. This series contains manuscripts, typescripts, and translations related to the poet’s various projects. Each project makes up the four subseries in this series. Materials in this series span the years 1959-1990.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Francisco Zea, Carlos de; Colombia -- Poetry; Poets; Latin American Poetry; Poetry
INVENTORY
- Series I: Libros de Poesía
  - Subseries 1: El despertar de las piedras (Genesis)
    - Poema I, "La Tierra," drafts (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Poema II, "El poema," drafts, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Poema III, "Hojas," drafts, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Poema IV, "El otro," drafts, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Poema V, "La paradoja," drafts (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Poema VI, "El enajenado," drafts, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Poema VII, "Inmanencia," drafts (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Poema VIII, "Estatua falsa," drafts, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Poema IX, drafts, 1958, 1959, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Poema X, "Instantes," drafts (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Poema XI, drafts, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Poema XII, "Grietas," drafts, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Poema XIII, "Tiempo," drafts (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Poema XIV, "Preludio," drafts, 1972, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Poema XV, "Coda," drafts, 1959, 1986, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poema XVI, "Glosa del destierro," drafts, 1961, 1970, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poema XVII, "Bálsamo," drafts, 1960, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Poema XVIII, "Autorretrato," drafts, 1972, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Poema XIX, "El desarraigado," drafts, 1986, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Poema XX, "La caida," drafts, 1959, 1966, 1982, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Poema XXI, drafts, 1962, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Poema XXII, drafts, 1972, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Poema XXIII, drafts (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Poema XXIV, "Evocaciones," drafts, 1959, 1972, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Poema XXV, "El niño," drafts, 1972, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Poema XXVI, "Riqueza," drafts, 1959, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Poema XXVII, "El recuerdo," drafts, 1959, 1972, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Poema XXVIII, "Saudade," drafts, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Poema XXIX, drafts, 1959, 1966, 1987, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Poema XXX, drafts, 1960, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Poema XXXI, "El tejedor viejo," drafts, 1972, 1987, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Poema XXXII, "Entretiempo," drafts, 1960, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Poema XXXIII, "La conquista," drafts, 1959, 1972, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Poema XXXIV, "Canción," drafts, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Poema XXXV, "Alamos," drafts, 1959, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Poema y XXXVI, "En desvelo de diamante," drafts, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Poema y XXXVI, "Envio," drafts (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Poema y XXXVI, "Envio," "Parabola," drafts (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - List of dates, manuscript and typescript (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Corrections, manuscript and typescript (Box 2, Folder 5-8)
    - First version, typescript (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Second version, typescript, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Third version, typescript, 1957-1960, summer 1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Fourth version, typescript, 1957-1960, summer 1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Fifth version, typescript, 1957-1964, summer 1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Sixth version, typescript, summer 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Seventh version, typescript, summer 1966 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Eighth version, typescript, summer 1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Ninth version, typescript, summer 1972 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - untitled and undated version (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 2: Mozartiana (Genesis)
    - Sub-subseries 1: En modo mayor
      - "Alegría súbita," drafts, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - "Villancico," drafts, 1966, 1967, 1969, 1985, 1986, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - "Perro fiel," drafts, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - "El cuento del pozo," drafts, 1986, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - "La salamandra," drafts, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - "Navarra," drafts, 1986, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - "El rejoneador," drafts, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - "El galán," drafts, 1986, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - "La violeta," drafts, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - "Fragonard," drafts, 1979, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - "La luna, cuando levanta," drafts, 1950, 1966, 1987, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - "De un cancionera," Favor os pido," drafts, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - "De un cancionera," "Muchacha de Costa Rica:" drafts, 1960, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - "De un cancionera," "Eres la tierra mojada," drafts (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - "De un cancionera," "Hasta el remanso quieto de tu vida," drafts, 1959, 1966, 1986, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - "De un cancionera," "Volar como el pájaro inquieto," drafts, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - "De un cancionera," "Eres cual medianoche silenciosa," drafts, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - "De un cancionera," "Momentánea y permanente," drafts, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - "Curazao," drafts, 1959, 1966, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - "Boceto de un sueño," drafts, 1988, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Sub-subseries 2: En modo Menor
      - "Abriendo sus matices," drafts, 1960, 1966, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - "Las nubes bermejas," drafts, 1959, 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - "Y son tres fugas al viento," drafts, 1959, 1966, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - "Las olas son ejécito," drafts, 1960, 1966, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - "En el jardín del alma planté un dia," drafts, 1965, 1966, 1967, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - "Revuelo de los pájaros insomnes," drafts, 1959, 1966, 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - "Por el bosque en Ilamas," drafts, 1959, 1965, 1985, 1986,1988 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - "Los celos," drafts, 1986, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - "Tiresias," drafts, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - "Gabriela Mistral," drafts, 1960, 1962, 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - "Voz de Praga," draftes, 1966, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - "Chopin," drafts, 1986, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - "Oracion," drafts, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - "Cherubini," drafts, 1986, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Subseries 3: Ofrenda (Genesis)
    - Sub-subseries 1: Motu Proprio
      - "El Cristo de Amagá," drafts, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - "Evocación," drafts, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - "Elegía," drafts, 1984, 1985, 1987, 1988, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - "Juego de té," drafts, 1984, 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - "Tio Gustavo," drafts, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - "Solidaridad," drafts, 1984, 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - "Primavera," drafts, 1967, 1969, 1973, 1981, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - "Puerto Edén," drafts, 1967, 1973, 1981, 1983, 1985, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - "Otoño," drafts, 1966, 1981, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - "Zamora," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Grecia Y Roma
      - "La Pitonisa," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - "Filemón y Baucis," drafts, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - "Medea," drafts, 1986, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - "Casandra," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - "Electra," drafts, 1986, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - "Antígona," drafts, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - "Prócer republicano," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - "El Afortunado," drafts, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - "Avisos," drafts, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - "Una carta del César a los padres conscriptos," drafts, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - "Tiberio ante Roma," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - "Claudius Ultor," drafts, 1987, 1988, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - "Plotina," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - "Adriano," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - "Medallones," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - "Carcalla," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Sub-subseries 3: Del sur y del norte
      - "Milagro de Provenza," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - "Queja de Bretána," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - "El besamanos," drafts, 1966, 1967, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - "Manuel Paleólogo," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - "Pío II," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - "Federico de Montefeltro," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - "El Bucentauro," drafts, 1987, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      - "César Borgia," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 24)
      - "El buen señor de Sant’ Andrea," drafts, 1984, 1987, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 25)
      - "Federico Gonzaga," drafts, 1979, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - "A un triunfador," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - "Catalina de Aragón," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - "Catalina de Médicis," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - "Album de Clouet," drafts, 1987, 1988, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - "Castalión," drafts, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - "Crónica de Alemania en 1623," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - "Album de Callot," drafts, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - "Innocencio XII," drafts, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - "Madame d’Épinay," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - "Madame de Pompadour," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - "El Obispo de Autun ante el portal de San Lázaro," drafts, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - "El Temple," drafts, 1971, 1983, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - "La Princesa de Lamballe," drafts, 1971, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - "Danton," drafts, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - "Robespierre," drafts, 1984, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - "Matthew Arnold," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - "1916," drafts, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - "1917," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - "Woodrow Wilson," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - "Patmos," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Sub-subseries 4: España y América
      - "Don Alvaro e Luna," drafts, 1986, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - "El converso," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - "Hacia Tordesillas," drafts, 1986, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      - "El despido," drafts, 1967, 1969, 1973, 1981, 1984, 1986, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      - "Felipe II," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 26)
      - "Barroco quiteño," drafts, 1973, 1987, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 27)
      - "Utopía guaraní," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - "El pícaro," drafts, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - "El Conde-Duque de Olivares," drafts, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - "Los embrujados," drafts, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - "Godoy," drafts, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - "El caudillo," drafts, 1984, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Sub-subseries 5: Crisoles
      - "Grünewald," drafts, 1971, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - "Holbein el Joven," drafts, 1987, 1988, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - "Gabriel de Guilleragues," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - "A Goethe," drafts, 1965, 1967, 1984, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - "Schiller," drafts, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - "Mario de Sá-Carneiro," drafts, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - "Munch," drafts, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - "A Mondrian," 1984, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - "Proust," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - "A Rupert Brooke," drafts, 1965, 1967, 1984, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      - "Oyendo a Gardel," drafts, 1986, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      - "A Teresa de la Parra," drafts, 1965, 1973, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - "A José María González Concha," drafts, 1965, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - "Magritte," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 20)
      - "Delvaux," drafts, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 21)
      - "Edward Hopper," 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 22)
      - ‘George Tooker," drafts, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 23)
      - "Callas," drafts, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Sub-subseries 6: Teofanía
      - "Hölderlin," drafts, 1965, 1967, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Subseries 4: Materials relating to publication of Libros de Poesía
    - "Rough draft A," first draft, manuscript, summer 1987 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - "Rough draft B," draft sent to the Library of Congress, Copyright Office, typescript (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - "Rough draft C," draft sent to the publisher Los Libros de la Frontera, typescript (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
    - Ofrenda, fragments, manuscript (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Ofrenda, outlines, manuscript (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Ofrenda, notes, manuscript (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Ofrenda, themes, manuscript (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Ofrenda, corrections, manuscript (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Table of contents, rough drafts, typescript and manuscript (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Autobiographical notes, typescript and manuscript (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Galley corrections (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1988-1990 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Complimentary rough drafts sent to (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Complimentary publications sent to (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Bibliography of poems (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Poems published in newspapers, 1965, 1973, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Poems published in magazines, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Letters of rejection, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Advertisement for poetry contest, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - El despertar de las piedras, manuscript and typescript, 1959, 1960, 1962, 1965, 1966, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 6-59)
    - El despertar de las piedras, manuscript and typescript, 1959, 1960, 1962, 1965, 1966, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 1-72)
- Series II: Other Writings
  - Subseries 1: VARIA, MISCELLANEOUS (Paralipómenos, Chronicles 1 & 2)
    - Unpublished, poetry fragments, manuscripts, 1959, 1960, 1965, 1966, 1967, 1968, 1984, 1986, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 1-18)
    - Poetry translations of Juan Ramón Jiménez, manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 19-20)
    - Poetry translations of Juan Ramón Jiménez, final draft, typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Poetry translations of Juan Ramón Jiménez, rough drafts, manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Review of Carlos de Francisco Zea’s translations of Ramón Jiménez, The Fifties, 1959, postcards of Juan Ramón Jiménez and his home, undated (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Poetry translations, miscellaneous authors, manuscript and typescript, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Poetry translations, exact in English, manuscript and typescript, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Poetry translations, in English, manuscript and typescript, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Fiction, in English, manuscript and typescript (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Drama, rough drafts, manuscript (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - Miscellaneous projects, manuscript and typescript (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - Notes, manuscript and typescript (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Subseries 2: "THE WONDER OF WORDS"
    - "The Forum Speeches in Julius Caesar," annotated typescript, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - "Goethe’s ‘Euphrozyne’," annotated typescript, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - "Goethe’s ‘Auf Miedings Tod’," annotated typescript, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - "Goethe’s ‘Epilog zu Schillers Glocke’," annotated typescript, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - "Keats’ ‘Ode to a Nightingale’," annotated typescript, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - "Browning’s ‘The Bishop Orders His Tomb at Saint Praxed’s Church’," annotated typescript, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - "Tennyson’s ‘Tears, Idle Tears’," annotated typescript, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - "The Sensation of ‘Spleen’ in Baudelaire," annotated typescript, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - "David Hume on the Origin and Maintenance of Society," annotated typescript, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - "The Early Portraiture of Ingres," annotated typescript, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - "Goethe’s Conception of Human Activity," thesis, annotated typescript, undated (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
  - Subseries 3: LA GARGANTA PRESTADA
    - Plan, Apologia A, manuscript, 1987, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 8-9)
    - Apologia B, typescript and manuscript, 1989, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
    - "Prodigio," typescript, manuscript, 1988, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 4: EXTRA
    - Poetry, fragments, manuscripts, 1967, 1980, 1986, 1987, 1988, 1989, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 13-19)